So I know TED is about a lot of things that are big,
أعلم أن TED يدور حول الكثير من الأشياء الهامة والملهمة،
but I want to talk to you about something very small.
ولكنني أريد التحدث إليكم عن شيء صغير جداً.
So small, it's a single word.
صغير جداً، وعلى هيئة كلمة واحدة.
The word is "misfit."
الكلمة هي "غير ملائم".
It's one of my favorite words, because it's so literal.
إنها واحدة من كلماتي المفضلة، لأنها كلمة واقعية وموضوعية للغاية.
I mean, it's a person who sort of missed fitting in.
وأعني، أنها نوعاً ما تدل على شخص أضاع فرصة الاندماج والانسجام.
Or a person who fits in badly.
أو تدل على شخص يندمج وينسجم ولكن بشكل سيء.
Or this: "a person who is poorly adapted
أو تدل على الشخص الذي يتكيف بطريقة مزرية
to new situations and environments."
مع البيئات والأوضاع الجديدة.
I'm a card-carrying misfit.
أنا أحمل بطاقة عدم الملاءمة.
And I'm here for the other misfits in the room,
وأنا هنا من أجل من هم على غراري في القاعة،
because I'm never the only one.
إذ أنني لست الشخص الوحيد على الإطلاق.
I'm going to tell you a misfit story.
سأحكي لكم قصة عن فكرة عدم الملاءمة.
Somewhere in my early 30s,
تقريبا وأنا في بداية الثالثين من عمري،
the dream of becoming a writer came right to my doorstep.
جاء حلمي أن أصبح كاتبة إلى عتبة منزلي.
Actually, it came to my mailbox
في الواقع، جاء إلى صندوق بريدي
in the form of a letter that said I'd won a giant literary prize
على هيئة رسالة ذكر فيها أنني قد حصلت على جائزة أدبية عملاقة
for a short story I had written.
لقصة قصيرة كنت قد كتبتها في الماضي.
The short story was about my life as a competitive swimmer
كانت القصة القصيرة عن حياتي كسباحة تنافسية
and about my crappy home life,
وعن حياتي المنزلية المزرية،
and a little bit about how grief and loss can make you insane.
وقليلاً عن كيف يمكن لللحزن والخسارة ـن يجعلاك مجنوناً.
The prize was a trip to New York City to meet big-time editors and agents
وكانت الجائزة عبارة عن رحلة إلى نيويورك للقاء نخبة من رؤساء ووكلاء التحرير
and other authors.
ومؤلفين آخرين.
So kind of it was the wannabe writer's dream, right?
إذ أنها نوعاً ما حلم جميع الكتاب الجدد، أليس كذلك؟
You know what I did the day the letter came to my house?
هل تعرفون ما الذي فعلته في اليوم الذي وصلت فيه الرسالة إلى بيتي؟
Because I'm me,
ولأنني أتصرف على طبيعتي،
I put the letter on my kitchen table,
وضعت الرسالة على طاولة المطبخ،
I poured myself a giant glass of vodka
وسكبت لنفسي كوباً عملاقا من الفودكا
with ice and lime,
مع الثلج وحامض ليمون،
and I sat there in my underwear for an entire day,
وجلست هناك في ملابسي الداخلية ولمدة يوم كامل،
just staring at the letter.
أحدق في تلك الرسالة فقط.
I was thinking about all the ways I'd already screwed my life up.
كنت أفكر في كل الطرق التي من خلالها قمت بهدر حياتي.
Who the hell was I to go to New York City
من أنا لأذهب إلى مدينة نيويورك
and pretend to be a writer?
وأدعي بأنني كاتبة؟
Who was I?
من أنا لأفعل ذلك؟
I'll tell you.
سوف أخبركم.
I was a misfit.
كنت غير ملائمة في الماضي
Like legions of other children,
مثل حشود من الأطفال الآخرين،
I came from an abusive household
جئت من أسرة مسيئة ومؤذية
that I narrowly escaped with my life.
إذ أنني بالكاد استطعت النجاة بحياتي.
I already had two epically failed marriages underneath my belt.
مررت بتجربتين ملحميتين خائبتين من الزواج.
I'd flunked out of college not once but twice
وتركت الجامعة ليس لمرة واحدة بل لمرتين
and maybe even a third time that I'm not going to tell you about.
وربما لمرة ثالثة ولكنني لن أقول لكم عنها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I'd done an episode of rehab for drug use.
ومررت بمرحلة تأهيل لتعاطي المخدرات.
And I'd had two lovely staycations in jail.
وقضيت رحلتين جميلتين في السجن.
So I'm on the right stage.
لذا أعتقد أنني على المسرح المناسب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the real reason, I think, I was a misfit,
ولكنني أعتقد أن السبب الحقيقي لكوني غير ملائمة،
is that my daughter died the day she was born,
هو وفاة ابنتي حال ولادتها،
and I hadn't figured out how to live with that story yet.
ولم أكتشف بعد كيفية العيش مع هذه المأساة.
After my daughter died I also spent a long time homeless,
قضيت وبعد وفاة ابنتي وقتا طويلاً بلا مأوى،
living under an overpass
أعيش تحت أحد الجسور
in a kind of profound state of zombie grief and loss
في نوع من حالة حزن وخسارة عميقة
that some of us encounter along the way.
والذي يصادفها البعض منا خلال حياته.
Maybe all of us, if you live long enough.
وربما كل واحد منا، إذا كنت لتعيش لفترة كافية.
You know, homeless people are some of our most heroic misfits,
أتعلمون، المشردون هم أكثر الاشخاص الغير الملائمين بطولةً بيننا،
because they start out as us.
لأنهم يبدؤون على شاكلتنا.
So you see, I'd missed fitting in to just about every category out there:
وكما ترون، فقد ضيعت فرصة الاندماج والملائمة مع معظم الفئات الاجتماعية:
daughter, wife, mother, scholar.
ابنة، زوجة، أم، عالمة.
And the dream of being a writer
وحلمي بأن أصبح كاتبة
was really kind of like a small, sad stone in my throat.
كان في الحقيقة مثل، حجر صغير محزن في حلقي.
It was pretty much in spite of myself that I got on that plane
وكان على الرغم من نفسي وإلى حد كبير، أن صعدت تلك الطائرة
and flew to New York City,
وحلقت إلى مدينة نيويورك،
where the writers are.
حيث المؤلفون.
Fellow misfits, I can almost see your heads glowing.
زملائي غير الملائمين، يمكنني تقريباً رؤية رؤوسكم متوهجة.
I can pick you out of a room.
أستطيع تمييزكم في غرفة ما.
At first, you would've loved it.
في البداية، كنتم لتحبون ذلك.
You got to choose the three famous writers you wanted to meet,
كان لك اختيار ثلاثة من المؤلفين المشاهير والذين ترغب في لقائهم،
and these guys went and found them for you.
وقام هؤلاء الأشخاص بإيجادهم لك.
You got set up at the Gramercy Park Hotel,
والحصول على إقامة في فندق غرامرسى بارك،
where you got to drink Scotch late in the night
حيث تستطيع شرب السكوتش في وقت متأخر من الليل
with cool, smart, swank people.
مع أشخاص لطفاء، أذكياء ومتباهين.
And you got to pretend you were cool and smart and swank, too.
وكان عليك حينها الادعاء بأنك لطيف، ذكي ومتباه أيضاً
And you got to meet a bunch of editors and authors and agents
وتمكنت حينها من لقاء مجموعة من المحررين والمؤلفين ووكلاء النشر
at very, very fancy lunches and dinners.
خلال وجبات الغداء والعشاء الفاخرة للغاية.
Ask me how fancy.
إسالوني عن مدى فخامتها؟
Audience: How fancy?
(الجمهور) ما مدى فخامتها؟
Lidia Yuknavitch: I'm making a confession: I stole three linen napkins --
سأعترف لكم بأمر: لقد قمت بسرقة ثلاثة مناديل من الكتان
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
from three different restaurants.
من ثلاث مطاعم مختلفة.
And I shoved a menu down my pants.
وقمت بوضع قائمة الطعام في سروالي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I just wanted some keepsakes so that when I got home,
أردت فقط الاحتفاظ بتذكارات لحين عودتي الى المنزل،
I could believe it had really happened to me.
لأتمكن من تصديق حدوث ذلك لي بالفعل.
You know?
هل فهمتم قصدي؟
The three writers I wanted to meet
المؤلفات الثلاثة واللاتي رغبت
were Carole Maso, Lynne Tillman and Peggy Phelan.
في لقائهن هن "كارول ماسو"، "لين تيلمان" و"بيغي فيلان".
These were not famous, best-selling authors,
لم يكن من المشاهير، ولا صاحبات أكثر الكتب مبيعاً،
but to me, they were women-writer titans.
لكن بالنسبة لي، كن من عمالقة المؤلفيات من النساء.
Carole Maso wrote the book that later became my art bible.
كتبت "كارول ماسو" الكتاب الذي أصبح لاحقاً دليلي الفني.
Lynne Tillman gave me permission to believe
أعطتني "لين تيلمان" إذناً للاعتقاد
that there was a chance my stories could be part of the world.
بأن هناك فرصة لقصصي أن تصبح جزء من العالم.
And Peggy Phelan reminded me
وذكرتني "بيغي فيلان"
that maybe my brains could be more important than my boobs.
أنه من الممكن لعقلي أن يكون أهم بكثير من جسدي.
They weren't mainstream women writers,
لم يكن من النساء الكاتبات في الأدب والخيال العام،
but they were cutting a path through the mainstream
ولكن شققن طريقهن
with their body stories,
من خلال مجموعة من المؤلفات،
I like to think, kind of the way water cut the Grand Canyon.
وأحب أن أعتقد أنها كشق المياه طريقاً لها في الوادي العظيم.
It nearly killed me with joy
كانت الفرحة على وشك القضاء علي.
to hang out with these three over-50-year-old women writers.
لأتمكن من لقاء مجموعة المؤلفات الثلاث والذي يفوق عمرهن الخمسين عاماً.
And the reason it nearly killed me with joy
وسبب كوني حينها فرحة حتى الموت
is that I'd never known a joy like that.
وهو أنني لم اأعرف فرحة مثلها من قبل.
I'd never been in a room like that.
ولم أكن في غرفة كهذه من قبل.
My mother never went to college.
لم تذهب أمي إلى الجامعة أبداً.
And my creative career to that point
ومسيرتي الإبداعية ولغاية هذه النقطة
was a sort of small, sad, stillborn thing.
كانت نوعاً ما صغيرة، حزينة، كمولود ميت.
So kind of in those first nights in New York I wanted to die there.
وفي الليالي الاولى تمنيت نوعاً ما الموت في مدينة نيو يورك
I was just like, "Kill me now. I'm good. This is beautiful."
وأحسست حينها "أقتلني الآن. لا أمانع. هذا رائع."
Some of you in the room will understand what happened next.
بعضكم هنا سيفهم ما سيحدث لاحقاً.
First, they took me to the offices of Farrar, Straus and Giroux.
أولاً. رافقوني إلى مكاتب شركة "فارار وستراوس وجيرو" للنشر.
Farrar, Straus and Giroux was like my mega-dream press.
الآن شركة "فارار وستراوس وجيرو" للنشر هي بمثابة حلم ضخم بالنسبة لي.
I mean, T.S. Eliot and Flannery O'Connor were published there.
"توماس ستيرنز إليوت" و"فلانري أوكونور" تم نشرها هناك.
The main editor guy sat me down and talked to me for a long time,
جلس معي رئيس التحرير وقام بالتحدث معي لمدة طويلة،
trying to convince me I had a book in me
محاولاً إقناعي أن هناك كتاباً في داخلي.
about my life as a swimmer.
عن حياتي كسباحة.
You know, like a memoir.
على شكل مذكرات.
The whole time he was talking to me,
طوال الوقت وهو يتحدث إلي،
I sat there smiling and nodding like a numb idiot,
كنت جالسة وأنا أبتسم وأهز رأسي كحمقاء فاقدة للحس،
with my arms crossed over my chest,
وذراعي مكتوفتان على صدري،
while nothing, nothing, nothing came out of my throat.
في حين لم يخرج أي شيء من حنجرتي على الإطلاق.
So in the end, he patted me on the shoulder
وفي النهاية، ربت على كتفي
like a swim coach might.
كما يفعل مدرب السباحة.
And he wished me luck
وتمنى لي التوفيق
and he gave me some free books
وأعطاني بعض الكتب المجانية
and he showed me out the door.
ورافقني إلى خارج الباب.
Next, they took me to the offices of W.W. Norton,
ومن ثم رافقوني إلى مكاتب شركة "وليام واردر نورتون" للنشر،
where I was pretty sure I'd be escorted from the building
وكنت حينها متأكدة على أنها ستتم مرافقي لخارج المبنى
just for wearing Doc Martens.
فقط لارتدائي حذاء من نوع "دوكتر مارتنز".
But that didn't happen.
ولكن ذلك لم يحدث.
Being at the Norton offices
وجودي في مكاتب شركة "وليام واردر نورتون" للنشر
felt like reaching up into the night sky and touching the moon
ألهمني إحساساً وكأنني أحاول الوصول ليلاً إلى السماء ولمس القمر
while the stars stitched your name across the cosmos.
بينما تقوم النجوم بحياكة اسمك في جميع أنحاء الكون.
I mean, that's how big a deal it was to me.
أعني، هذا هو مدى عظم الأمر بالنسبة لي.
You get it?
هل وصلتكم الفكرة؟
Their lead editor, Carol Houck Smith,
اقتربت رئيسة تحرير شركة "نورتون"، "كارول هاوك سميث"،
leaned over right in my face with these beady, bright, fierce eyes
من وجهي تماماً بعيونها الخرزية، الذكية، الشرسة
and said, "Well, send me something then, immediately!"
وقالت "حسناً إذا، أرسلي لي شيئا، في الحال"
See, now most people, especially TED people,
الآن، معظم الأشخاص وخاصة العاملون في TED،
would have run to the mailbox, right?
سيهرعون جرياً لصندوق البريد، أليس كذلك؟
It took me over a decade to even imagine
استغرق مني ذلك أكثر من عشر سنوات حتى لأتخيل
putting something in an envelope and licking a stamp.
وضع شيء في مغلف والقيام بلعق الطوابع.
On the last night,
وفي الليلة الأخيرة،
I gave a big reading at the National Poetry Club.
قدمت قراءة مطولة في نادي الشعر الوطني.
And at the end of the reading,
وفي نهاية القراءة،
Katharine Kidde of Kidde, Hoyt &amp; Picard Literary Agency,
قامت كاثرين كيدي من وكالة "كيدي، هويت وبيكارد" الأدبية،
walked straight up to me and shook my hand
بالمجيء إلي ومصافحة يدي.
and offered me representation, like, on the spot.
وقدموا لي الرعاية الأدبية، على الفور.
I stood there and I kind of went deaf.
وقفت حينها وأصابني نوع من الصمم.
Has this ever happened to you?
هل حدث هذا الشيء لكم من قبل؟
And I almost started crying
وكنت على وشك البكاء
because all the people in the room were dressed so beautifully,
إذ أن جميع الحاضرين كانوا يرتدون أجمل الثياب
and all that came out of my mouth was:
وكل الذي خرج من فمي هو:
"I don't know. I have to think about it."
"لا أعلم. يجب أن أفكر في الموضوع."
And she said, "OK, then," and walked away.
وحينها قالت، "حسنا إذاً" وغادرت.
All those open hands out to me, that small, sad stone in my throat ...
وكل هذه الأيادي الممتدة لي، مع إحساس الحجر الصغير المحزن في حلقي
You see, I'm trying to tell you something about people like me.
فكما ترون فإنني أحاول أن أشرح لكم عمن هم على شاكلتي.
Misfit people -- we don't always know how to hope or say yes
الأشخاص غير الملائمون-- لانعلم دائما كيف نأمل أو نقول نعم
or choose the big thing,
أو نختار الشيء المميز،
even when it's right in front of us.
وحتى وان كان هذا الشيء أمامنا مباشرةً.
It's a shame we carry.
إنه خزي نقوم بحمله.
It's the shame of wanting something good.
إنه الخزي من رغبة الأشياء المميزة.
It's the shame of feeling something good.
إنه الخزي من الإحساس بشيء مميز.
It's the shame of not really believing we deserve to be in the room
إنه الخزي من عدم اعتقادنا بأننا نستحق الجلوس في نفس الغرفة
with the people we admire.
مع الأشخاص الذين نعجب بهم.
If I could, I'd go back and I'd coach myself.
لو استطعت، لعدت ولقمت بتدريب نفسي.
I'd be exactly like those over-50-year-old women who helped me.
وأصبحت مثل النساء اللاتي قدمن لي المساعدة والذي يتجاوز عمرهن الخمسين عاماً.
I'd teach myself how to want things,
ولعلمت نفسي كيفية الرغبة في الأشياء.
how to stand up, how to ask for them.
وكيفية الإقبال والقيام بطلب ما أرغب فيه.
I'd say, "You! Yeah, you! You belong in the room, too."
كنت سأقول: "أنت. نعم أنت. أنت تنتمي لهذه القاعة أيضاً"
The radiance falls on all of us,
عندها سيسلط الضوء على كل واحد منا،
and we are nothing without each other.
وسنعلم حينها أنه لا قيمة لأي منا من دون الآخر.
Instead, I flew back to Oregon,
لكن عوضاً عن ذلك، عدت إلى ولاية أوريغون،
and as I watched the evergreens and rain come back into view,
وبينما كنت أشاهد المطر والمناظر الدائمة الخضرة وهي تعود إلى الحياة،
I just drank many tiny bottles of airplane "feel sorry for yourself."
شربت العديد من زجاجات "أشعر بالأسف لنفسك" الصغيرة والتي تقدم على متن الطائرة.
I thought about how, if I was a writer, I was some kind of misfit writer.
وفكرت كيف سأكون في حال كنت كاتبة، سأكون عندها كاتبة غير ملائمة.
What I'm saying is,
كل ما أقوله هو،
I flew back to Oregon without a book deal,
أنه حال عودتي الى أوريغون دون عقد تأليف،
without an agent,
ودون وكيل نشر،
and with only a headful and heart-ful of memories
ومعي فقط عقل وقلب مليء بالذكريات
of having sat so near
حول جلوسي القريب جدا ً من
the beautiful writers.
المؤلفين الرائعين.
Memory was the only prize I allowed myself.
كانت الذاكرة هي الجائزة الوحيدة والتي سمحت بها لنفسي.
And yet, at home in the dark,
ومع ذلك، وأنا في المنزل جالسة في الظلام.
back in my underwear,
وفي ملابسي الداخلية مرة أخرى،
I could still hear their voices.
كان ما زال بوسعي أن أسمع أصواتهم.
They said, "Don't listen to anyone who tries to get you to shut up
قالوا: "لا تستمع لأي شخص يحاول إجبارك على الصمت
or change your story."
أو على تغيير قصتك".
They said, "Give voice to the story only you know how to tell."
قالوا، "اعطِ صوتا لقصة أنت فقط من يعرف أن يرويها"
They said, "Sometimes telling the story
قالوا، "أن القيام برواية القصة أحياناً
is the thing that saves your life."
هو الشيء الذي ينقذ حياتك".
Now I am, as you can see, the woman over 50.
الآن أنا، وكما ترون، المرأة التي يتجاوز عمرها الخمسون عاماً.
And I'm a writer.
أنا مؤلفة.
And I'm a mother.
وأنا أم.
And I became a teacher.
وأصبحت معلمة.
Guess who my favorite students are.
تخيلوا من هم طلابي المفضلون.
Although it didn't happen the day
على الرغم من عدم حدوث ذلك في اليوم
that dream letter came through my mailbox,
الذي تلقيت فيه رسالة الحلم في صندوق بريدي
I did write a memoir,
قمت بكتابة مذكرة،
called "The Chronology of Water."
تسمى "التسلسل الزمني للمياه".
In it are the stories of how many times I've had to reinvent a self
في هذه القصة كتبت كم مرة كان عليّ إعادة اختراع نفسي.
from the ruins of my choices,
من أنقاض خياراتي،
the stories of how my seeming failures were really just weird-ass portals
وكيف أن مواطن الفشل لم تكن سوى بوابات غريبة الأطوار
to something beautiful.
لشيء جميل.
All I had to do was give voice to the story.
كل ما كان عليّ فعله هو إعطاء صوت للقصة.
There's a myth in most cultures about following your dreams.
هناك أسطورة في معظم الثقافات حول اتباع أحلامك.
It's called the hero's journey.
وتدعى رحلة البطل.
But I prefer a different myth,
ولكنني أفضل أسطورة مختلفة،
that's slightly to the side of that
قد توائم أسطورة رحلة البطل
or underneath it.
أو تختلف عنها قليلا.
It's called the misfit's myth.
تسمى أسطورة الشخص غير الملائم.
And it goes like this:
وهي كالتالي:
even at the moment of your failure,
حتى في لحظة فشلك،
right then, you are beautiful.
حينها تماما، أنت رائع.
You don't know it yet,
أنت لا تعرف ذلك بعد،
but you have the ability to reinvent yourself
وهو أن لديك القدرة على إعادة اختراع نفسك
endlessly.
وبلا نهاية.
That's your beauty.
وهذه هي روعتك.
You can be a drunk,
من الممكن أن تكون سكيرا،
you can be a survivor of abuse,
ومن الممكن أن تكون أحد الناجين من اعتداء،
you can be an ex-con,
ومن الممكن أن تكون سجينا سابقا.
you can be a homeless person,
ومن الممكن أن تكون بلا مأوى،
you can lose all your money or your job or your husband
ومن الممكن أن تفقد مالك أو عملك أو زوجك
or your wife, or the worst thing of all,
أو زوجتك، أو أن تفقد أسوأ شيء على الإطلاق،
a child.
أن تفقد طفلك.
You can even lose your marbles.
ومن الممكن أيضاً أن تفقد عقلك.
You can be standing dead center in the middle of your failure
قد تكون واقفاً تماماً في وسط فشلك
and still, I'm only here to tell you,
ومع ذلك، أنا هنا لأقول لك،
you are so beautiful.
أنت في غاية الروعة.
Your story deserves to be heard,
تستحق قصتك على أن تسمع،
because you, you rare and phenomenal misfit,
لأنك، يا أيها الشخص غير الملائم النادر والاستثنائي،
you new species,
يا أيها النوع الجديد،
are the only one in the room
أنت الشخص الوحيد في هذه القاعة
who can tell the story
والذي يمكنه حكاية القصة،
the way only you would.
في الطريقة التي تستطيع أنت فقط القيام بها.
And I'd be listening.
وسأكون حينها مصغية.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)